

warrenlr@gmail.com 778 . 386 . 4192

renewarren.ca

# About me:

I am a Researcher with over 20 years experience in biotechnology, genomics and computing research. I have played a central role in managing the bioinformatics of large international collaborations to decrypt the genomes of Rhodococus, Cryptococcus, spruce and bullfrog. I developed the first program for genome assembly with then emerging short DNA sequences (SSAKE) and pioneered the development of genomics technologies that enabled the discovery of Fusobacterium in colon cancer, one of Time Magazine's top ten medical breakthrough of 2011.

I currently lead the BC Genome Sciences Centre's bioinformatics technology lab highperformance computing group. In that role, I have conceptualized and developed/led the development of genome scaffolders for Oxford nanopore (LINKS) and 10XG data (ARCS). I am eager to take on additional challenges and leadership.

Language spoken and written: French & English

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Coordinator Sep 2010 -

Present

BC Cancer Agency – Genome Sciences Centre, Vancouver BC

- Provide project leadership, expertise, guidance
- · Plan / coordinate group activities
- Supervise / mentor biologists and programmers
- Conceptualize / innovate development of new bioinformatics technologies
- Write research grant proposals
- Interview candidates / teach and train personnel

Jan 2002 – Mar 2010

## Bioinformatician

BC Cancer Agency – Genome Sciences Centre, Vancouver BC

- Lead bioinformatics software R&D
- Published research in reputed journals / international conferences
- Developed marketing (web portals / news release)
- Supervised a team of biologists and programmers
- Interviewed job candidates, taught and trained employees

Jan 2000 -Dec 2001

#### Officer

National Research Council - Biotechnology Research Institute, Montreal QC

- Co-engineered a system for regulating gene expression in cells
- Designed, fabricated and tested components of the DNA "gene switch"
- Work led to a patent, technology sold to company
- Integrated technology in viral and cell systems

## **EDUCATION**

| Sep 2005 –<br>Jun 2006 | People and Project Management Courses Provincial Health Services Authority of British Columbia, Canada  |
|------------------------|---|
| Sep 2000 –<br>Dec 2001 | Computer Science Courses Concordia University, Montréal, Canada   |
| Jun 1997 –<br>Aug 1999 | MSc Biochemistry & Molecular Biology University of British Columbia, Vancouver, Canada Studies of the regulation of rod photoreceptors cGMP-gated channels                |
| Sep 1994 –<br>May 1997 | <b>BSc Biochemistry,</b> dean Honour list mention in 1995 and 1996 Université de Montréal, Montréal, Canada Structure-function studies of the transcription factor Nkx2-5 |

# ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

| 2015, 16 | Recipient of the John Jambor Knowledge Fund travel award               |
|----------|--|
| 2011     | Interviewed by NTN24 channel for Fusobacterium discovery colon cancer  |
| 2009     | Interviewed by Genome Technology to discuss next-generation sequencing |
| 2007     | Interviewed by GenomeWeb for the development of SSAKE                  |
| 1998     | UBC Graduate Fellowship awarded for MSc                                |
| 1997     | Fonds de la Recherche en Santé Québec (FRSQ) awarded for BSc           |
| 1996     | Bursary from FRSQ for BSc honour's research project                    |
| 1995     | Worked at NASA to coordinate the crystallization of proteins under     |
|          | microgravity [CMIX-4 payload, space shuttle Endeavour]                 |

| PRESENTATIONS (selected from 14) |  |  |
|----------------------------------|--|--|
| 2015, 16                         | Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology, Dublin UK / Orlando USA - talks |  |
| 2008, 12, 15                     | Pacific Symposium on Biocomputing, Kona, Hawaii, USA – posters             |  |
| 2010                             | Sequencing, Finishing and Analysis in the Future, Santa Fe USA – talk      |  |
| 2009                             | Advances in Genome Biology and Technology, Marco Island USA – poster       |  |
| 2007                             | Synthetic Biology 3.0 conference, Zürich, Switzerland – talk               |  |

## **PUBLICATIONS** (selected from ~50)

Yeo S\*, Coombe L\*, Chu J, Warren RL\*, Birol I. (2017) ARCS: Assembly Roundup by Chromium Scaffolding, TBD

Coombe L\*, Warren RL\*, et al. (2016) Assembly of the complete Sitka spruce chloroplast genome using 10X Genomics' GemCode sequencing data. PLoS ONE. 11(9): e0163059

Warren RL, et al. (2015) LINKS: Scalable, alignment-free scaffolding of draft genomes with long reads. GigaScience 4:35

Warren RL, et al. (2012) Derivation of HLA types from shotgun sequence datasets. Genome Med. 4:95 Castellarin M\*, Warren RL\*, et al. (2012) Fusobacterium nucleatum infection is prevalent in human colorectal carcinoma. Genome Research. 22:299-306

Warren RL, et al. (2007) Assembling millions of short DNA sequences using SSAKE. Bioinformatics.

E Allen-Vercoe, R Holt, R Moore, R Warren. Detection of fusobacterium in a gastrointestinal sample to diagnose gastrointestinal cancer. US Patent App. 13/877,421 / WO Patent 2,012,045,150

## REFERENCES

Available upon request

<sup>\*</sup>co-first authors